<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Ngama, Steeve</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Korte, Lisa</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Bindelle, Jérôme</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Vermeulen, Cédric</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Poulsen, John R.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-08-15T17:12:11Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2016-08-15T17:12:11Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: How bees deter elephants: beehive trials with forest elephants (Loxodonta africana cyclotis) in Gabon</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.rj592</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>In Gabon, like elsewhere in Africa, crops are often sources of conflict between humans and wildlife. Wildlife damage to crops can drastically reduce income, amplifying poverty and creating a negative perception of wild animal conservation among rural people. In this context, crop-raiding animals like elephants quickly become “problem animals”. To deter elephants from raiding crops beehives have been successfully employed in East Africa; however, this method has not yet been tested in Central Africa. We experimentally examined whether the presence of Apis mellifera adansonii, the African honey bee species present in Central Africa, deters forest elephants (Loxodonta Africana cyclotis) from feeding on fruit trees. We show for the first time that the effectiveness of beehives as deterrents of elephants is related to bee activity. Empty hives and those housing colonies of low bee activity do not deter elephants all the time; but beehives with high bee activity do. Although elephant disturbance of hives does not impede honey production, there is a tradeoff between deterrence and the quantity of honey produced. To best achieve the dual goals of deterring elephants and producing honey colonies must maintain an optimum activity level of 40 to 60 bee movements per minute. Thus, beehives colonized by Apis mellifera adansonii bees can be effective elephant deterrents, but people must actively manage hives to maintain bee colonies at the optimum activity level.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>honey bees</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>forest elephants</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Loxodonta cyclotis</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Gabon</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0155690</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.rj592/1</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.rj592/2</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.rj592/3</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>