<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Naniwadekar, Rohit S.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Shukla, Ushma L.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Isvaran, Kavita</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Datta, Aparajita</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-03-23T18:56:35Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2015-03-23T18:56:35Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Reduced hornbill abundance associated with low seed arrival and altered recruitment in a hunted and logged tropical forest</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.1cf35</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Logging and hunting are two key direct threats to the survival of wildlife in the tropics, and also disrupt important ecosystem processes. We investigated the impacts of these two factors on the different stages of the seed dispersal cycle, including abundance of plants and their dispersers and dispersal of seeds and recruitment, in a tropical forest in north-east India. We focused on hornbills, which are important seed dispersers in these forests, and their food tree species. We compared abundances of hornbill food tree species in a site with high logging and hunting pressures (heavily disturbed) with a site that had no logging and relatively low levels of hunting (less disturbed) to understand logging impacts on hornbill food tree abundance. We compared hornbill abundances across these two sites. We, then, compared the scatter-dispersed seed arrival of five large-seeded tree species and the recruitment of four of those species. Abundances of hornbill food trees that are preferentially targeted by logging were two times higher in the less disturbed site as compared to the heavily disturbed site while that of hornbills was 22 times higher. The arrival of scatter-dispersed seeds was seven times higher in the less disturbed site. Abundances of recruits of two tree species were significantly higher in the less disturbed site. For another species, abundances of younger recruits were significantly lower while that of older recruits were higher in the heavily disturbed site. Our findings suggest that logging reduces food plant abundance for an important frugivore-seed disperser group, while hunting diminishes disperser abundances, with an associated reduction in seed arrival and altered recruitment of animal-dispersed tree species in the disturbed site. Based on our results, we present a conceptual model depicting the relationships and pathways between vertebrate-dispersed trees, their dispersers, and the impacts of hunting and logging on these pathways.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Seed dispersal</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>hornbill</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>hunting</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>logging</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Buceros bicornis</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Aceros nipalensis</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Rhyticeros undulatus</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Anorrhinus austeni</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Arunachal Pradesh</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:spatial>Namdapha Tiger Reserve</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:spatial>Miao Reserved Forest</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:spatial>North-east India</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0120062</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.1cf35/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>