<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Sylvester, Emma V.A.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Bentzen, Paul</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Bradbury, Ian R.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Clément, Marie</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Pearce, Jon</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Horne, John</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Beiko, Robert G.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-07-27T15:40:10Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2017-07-27T15:40:10Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Applications of random forest feature selection for fine-scale genetic population assignment</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.93h33</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Genetic population assignment used to inform wildlife management and conservation efforts requires panels of highly informative genetic markers and sensitive assignment tests. We explored the utility of machine-learning algorithms (random forest, regularized random forest, and guided regularized random forest) compared with FST ranking for selection of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) for fine-scale population assignment. We applied these methods to an unpublished SNP dataset for Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar) and a published SNP data set for Alaskan Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha). In each species, we identified the minimum panel size required to obtain a self-assignment accuracy of at least 90% using each method to create panels of 50-700 markers Panels of SNPs identified using random forest-based methods performed up to 7.8 and 11.2 percentage points better than FST-selected panels of similar size for the Atlantic salmon and Chinook salmon data, respectively. Self-assignment accuracy ≥90% was obtained with panels of 670 and 384 SNPs for each dataset, respectively, a level of accuracy never reached for these species using FST-selected panels. Our results demonstrate a role for machine-learning approaches in marker selection across large genomic datasets to improve assignment for management and conservation of exploited populations.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Fisheries Management</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Conservation Genetics</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Random Forest</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>SNP Selection</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Individual Assignment</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Salmo salar</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Labrador</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1111/eva.12524</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.93h33/1</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.93h33/2</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>