<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd" packageId="urn:uuid:c5169649-6139-47a3-9249-1e2d83ddc8cd" system="knb"><dataset><title>2016 Earthworm data from the Boundary Waters Canoe Area Wilderness, Minnesota, USA</title><creator id="5094544693437608"><individualName><givenName>Todd</givenName><surName>Wellnitz</surName></individualName><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2358-6334</userId></creator><pubDate>2016</pubDate><abstract><para>Factors controlling the spread of invasive earthworms in the forest ecosystems of Minnesota’s Boundary Waters Canoe Area Wilderness are poorly known. Believed to have been introduced by anglers who use them as bait, invasive earthworms can alter the physical and chemical properties of soil and modify forest plant communities. To examine factors influencing earthworm distribution and abundance, we sampled 38 islands across five lakes to assess the effects of campsites, fire, and entry point distance on earthworm density, biomass and species richness. We hypothesized that all three parameters would be greater on islands with campsites, lower on burned islands, and would decrease with distance from the wilderness entry point. In addition to sampling earthworms, we collected soil cores to examine soil organic matter and recorded ground and vegetation cover. </para><para>Campsite presence was the single most important factor affecting sampled earthworm communities; density, biomass and species richness were all higher on islands having campsites. Fire was associated with reduced earthworm density, but had no direct effects on earthworm biomass or species richness. Fire influenced earthworm biomass primarily through its negative relationship to groundcover and through an interaction with entry point distance. Distance affected density but no other factor. For islands with campsites, however, distance from the entry point had a counterintuitive effect in that earthworm biomass, which increased with entry point distance.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>Earthworm</keyword><keyword>Boundary Waters Canoe Area Wilderness</keyword><keyword>Fire</keyword><keyword>Campsites</keyword><keyword>Entry point distance</keyword><keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><intellectualRights><para>This work is dedicated to the public domain under the Creative Commons Universal 1.0 Public Domain Dedication. To view a copy of this dedication, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/.</para></intellectualRights><coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>Boundary Waters Canoe Area Wilderness</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>91.8</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>91.8</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>47.95</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>47.95</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><taxonomicCoverage><generalTaxonomicCoverage>Earthworms:
Juvenile Lumbricus
Dendrobaena octaedra	
Lumbricus rubellus
Eisenia fetida
Juvenile Aporrectodea 
Lumbricus terrestris
Aporrectodea rosea 
Octolasion 
Dendrodrilus terrestris 
Allolobophora chlorotice</generalTaxonomicCoverage><taxonomicClassification><taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName><taxonRankValue>Lumbricus</taxonRankValue></taxonomicClassification></taxonomicCoverage><temporalCoverage><singleDateTime><calendarDate>2016</calendarDate></singleDateTime></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="2337499722843354"><individualName><givenName>Todd</givenName><surName>Wellnitz</surName></individualName><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2358-6334</userId></contact><methods><methodStep><description><para>On 9 July 2016 we put in canoes at BWCA entry point 30 on Lake One and headed east along a route that skirted the northern edge of the 2011 Pagami Creek Fire (Fig. 1). Over 7 d we sampled 38 islands on lakes One, Two, Three, Four, Hudson and Insula. Islands were selected on the basis of their fire history (burned/not burned) and the presence/absence of campsites (Table 1). Island selection was made using maps showing campsite locations (Fisher map F4) and the area covered by the Pagami Creek Fire (USDA Pagami Creek Fire Map). Initial selection followed a balanced design for each combination of characteristics (i.e., burned/campsite, burned/no campsite, not burned/ campsite, not burned/no campsite). However, field sampling revealed islands marked as burned were not, and some campsites on burned islands could not be found. Consequently, these islands were discarded from our sample set and resulted in an unbalanced design.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Distances between islands and the entry point were examined using straight-line distances instead of hypothetical canoe travel distances because the latter can be highly variable. Canoeists and anglers need not follow direct pathways between lakes and islands, and side trips to explore fishing spots and campsite locations are common. Also, multiple pathways may exist for reaching islands, especially in geographically complex lakes such as Insula. Thus, determining actual travel routes becomes a problematic exercise whereas straight-line distances are easily made and independent of human choice.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Sampling islands followed a standard procedure: Upon reaching an island, its burn condition, campsite status and GPS coordinates were recorded. Following this, three sampling sites spaced equidistantly around the island’s perimeter and approximately 10 m inland were chosen using three criteria: 1) site accessibility from shore, 2) availability of flat and open ground, and 3) lack of dense underbrush allowing easy access to the ground for sampling. After reaching a site, a center point was established and the percent of understory vegetation cover and percent of exposed soil was estimated within a 1 m radius of the site center. Visual estimates of cover and exposure were made with the aid of a chart depicting the Braun-Blanquet percent cover classes. Percent exposed soil was converted into percent groundcover by subtracting values from 100. To assess soil organic matter, three soil cores were collected within the established 1 m radius. The upper 10 cm of each 2.5 cm diameter core was collected and combined in a plastic bag for later organic matter analysis in the lab.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Earthworms were sampled following the procedures outlined in Hale (2013). A mustard water solution was prepared by combining 240 ml of powdered mustard with 4 L of water. This solution acts as an irritant that when poured on the ground and allowed to soak into the soil causes worms to emerge as they attempt to avoid the mustard. Half of this mustard solution was poured inside a 0.2 m2 quadrat placed at the site’s center and emerging earthworms were collected with forceps and placed in 50 ml plastic centrifuge tubes. After 2 minutes, the remaining solution was poured into the quadrat and earthworms were collected until they stopped emerging. This procedure was repeated at each site and earthworms from all three sites were combined for each island and preserved in a solution of 70% isopropyl alcohol and 2% formalin. Field conditions made it impractical to clear earthworm guts prior to preservation. Back in the laboratory, earthworms were identified using Hale (2013) and counted. Worms from each site were then combined, dried and weighed to determine biomass.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>We used the loss-on-ignition method to determined soil organic matter. Soil was dried in an oven at 40 C for 7 days, then homogenized with mortar and pestle. Homogenized samples were put into pre-weighed porcelain crucibles and weighed, then ignited in a mufﬂe-furnace (Fisher Scientific Isotemp Muffle Furnace Model 550-126) at 550 C for 3 h. The samples were subsequently cooled, placed in a desiccator overnight, and then weighed to the nearest 0.001 g. so biomass could be calculated.</para></description></methodStep><sampling><studyExtent><description><para>The 4410 km2 BWCA Wilderness is located in Minnesota’s Superior National Forest (47°57' N, 91°48' W) and extends 185 km along the Minnesota/Ontario border (Fig. 1, inset). Designated as a wilderness area in 1978, the area contains approximately 1175 glacial lakes and hundreds of kilometers of rivers and streams (Heinselman, 1999). It is the largest Forest Service Wilderness area east of the Rocky Mountains and the most heavily used wilderness in the United States, with over 150,000 overnight and day-use visitors annually (Eagleston &#x26; Marion, 2017).  Lakes and waterways comprise approximately 20% of the Boundary Waters wilderness and cross-country canoe travel is made possible by a network of portage trails that connect lakes. Forests in the BWCA are a mixture of conifers and hardwoods that include various species of pine (Pinus banksiana, P. resinosa, and P. strobus), white cedar (Thuja occidentalis), balsam fir (Abies basamea), white spruce (Picea glauca), and hardwoods such as paper birch (Betula papyrifera), big-toothed aspen (Populus grandidentata) and white oak (Quercus alba) (Dickens, Gerhardt, &#x26; Collinge, 2005)</para><para>The climate of the BWCA region is hemiboreal with mild/cool summers and long winters (Köppen classification Dfb). Average July and January temperatures are 20° and -11° C, respectively, with temperature extremes of 32° and -40° C occurring (Dickens et al., 2005). Annual precipitation ranges 66-78 cm and occurs mostly in winter as snow (ca. 40%). Soils of the area are thin and acidic and overlay Canadian Shield bedrock. Charcoal is almost universal in upper soil layers, indicative of the key role fire has played in shaping this ecosystem (Heinselman, 1999).</para><para>Recreational access to the BWCA is controlled through a permit-based quota system that limits the number of people entering through each wilderness entry point. Visitors can obtain permits from May thru September and group sizes are limited to nine. Camping is restricted to approximately 2000 designated campsites established by the by U.S. Forest Service, that are unambiguously indicated by cast iron fire grates located at each site (Eagleston &#x26; Marion, 2017a).</para></description></studyExtent><samplingDescription><para>see information above</para></samplingDescription></sampling></methods><otherEntity><entityName>BWCA Earthworm data.xlsx</entityName><entityDescription>Earthworm density, biomass and richness data collected from islands in the Boundary Waters Canoe Area Wilderness. Also data on soil organic matte and percent cover of understory vegetation ground cover.</entityDescription><attributeList><attribute id="CwJWWslEaeppiR0Z9S0cG5XQe9HSF5"><attributeName>Island</attributeName><attributeLabel>Sampled island</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>Numeric identifier arbitrarily assigned</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><ordinal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Any text</definition><pattern>*</pattern></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></ordinal></measurementScale></attribute><attribute id="DVzyvAZTFCFemATXowxftwnNlTqRiD"><attributeName>Latitude, Longitude</attributeName><attributeLabel>Latitude and Longitude of locations</attributeLabel><attributeDefinition>These are the locations of samples islands</attributeDefinition><measurementScale><nominal><nonNumericDomain><textDomain><definition>Any text</definition><pattern>*</pattern></textDomain></nonNumericDomain></nominal></measurementScale></attribute></attributeList><entityType>application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet</entityType></otherEntity></dataset></eml:eml>