<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Zhang, Yunhai</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Loreau, Michel</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>He, Nianpeng</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Zhang, Guangming</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Han, Xingguo</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-02-27T20:12:10Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2017-02-27T20:12:10Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Mowing exacerbates the loss of ecosystem stability under nitrogen enrichment in a temperate grassland</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.sq15g</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Summary:&#xD;
1. Global reactive nitrogen (N) is projected to further increase in the coming years. Previous studies have demonstrated that N enrichment weakens the temporal stability of ecosystem primary productivity through decreased biodiversity and species asynchrony. Mowing is a globally common practice in grasslands; and infrequent mowing can maintain or increase plant diversity under N enrichment conditions. However, it is unclear how infrequent mowing affects ecosystem stability in the face of N enrichment.&#xD;
2. By independently manipulating the frequency (twice vs. monthly additions yr–1) and rate (i.e., 0, 1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15, 20, and 50 g N m–2 yr–1) of NH4NO3 inputs and mowing (unmown vs. mown) over three years (2011–2013) in a temperate grassland of northern China, we aimed to examine the interactive effects of N enrichment and mowing on ecosystem stability.&#xD;
3. The results show that mowing maintained a positive relationship between species richness and ecosystem stability despite N addition but that it exacerbated the negative effects of N addition on ecosystem stability. Mowing increased mean primary productivity and plant species richness, but it also increased the synchrony of population fluctuations and the variability of primary productivity under N enrichment, thereby contributing to a decline in ecosystem stability.&#xD;
4. Thus, our study reveals that infrequent mowing can buffer the negative effects of N enrichment on biodiversity to some extent and further increase primary productivity but it exacerbates the loss of ecosystem stability with N enrichment, thereby threatening local and/or semiarid regional food security.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Biodiversity</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>biomass harvest</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>community stability</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>clipping</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>nitrogen addition</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>nitrogen addition frequency</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>productivity</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>steppe</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>ecosystem</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>community</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>field</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:spatial>China</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.12850</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.sq15g/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>