<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Inclán, Diego J.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Cerretti, Pierfilippo</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Gabriel, Doreen</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Benton, Tim G.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Sait, Steven M.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Kunin, William E.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Gillespie, Mark A. K.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Marini, Lorenzo</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-05-08T21:23:03Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2015-05-08T21:23:03Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Organic farming enhances parasitoid diversity at the local and landscape scale</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7p1d3</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>1. The magnitude of the benefits derived from organic farming within contrasting managed landscapes remains unclear and, in particular, the potential scale-dependent response of insect parasitoids is relatively unexplored. Identifying the scale at which parasitoids are affected by organic farming will be an important step to enhance their conservation. 2. We sampled tachinid parasitoids at the centre and margin of arable and grassland fields on paired organic and conventional farms located in landscapes with different proportions of organic land. A total of 192 fields were sampled in two biogeographical regions of the UK. 3. We found that the positive effect of organic farming on tachinid parasitoid diversity can be observed at multiple spatial scales. At the local scale, we found higher abundance and species richness of tachinid parasitoids on organic than on conventional farms and on field margins than on field centres. At the landscape scale, the diversity of tachinids was higher in landscapes with higher proportions of organic land. At both scales, the positive effect of organic farming was clear for arable fields, while it was almost neutral for grasslands. 4. Synthesis and applications. Any attempt to enhance parasitoid diversity in agricultural landscapes needs to consider the local management in relation to the habitat type, location within the field and agricultural management in the surrounding landscape. To restore parasitoid diversity, the promotion of organic agriculture should aim to increase both the total extent of organic farming and the connectivity of individual farms. As the benefits of organic farming to biodiversity clearly spread beyond individual farm boundaries, any assessment of organic farming should consider these positive externalities.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Agricultural intensification</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Agri-environment schemes</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Biocontrol</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Natural enemies</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Scale-dependence</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Management</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Diptera</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Tachinidae</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>UK</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2664.12457</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7p1d3/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>