<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml
      packageId="nrs.875.1" system="knb"
      xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:ds="eml://ecoinformatics.org/dataset-2.1.1"
      xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1"
      xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">
<!-- Person who filled in the catalog entry form: Lynn McLaren -->
<!-- Form filled out at Fri Jan 17 20:22:24 2014 GMT -->
<access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst">
<allow>
  <principal>uid=nrsadmin,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>cn=knb-prod,o=NCEAS,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>all</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>uid=scir,o=unaffiliated,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal><permission>read</permission>
<permission>write</permission>
</allow>
<allow>
  <principal>public</principal><permission>read</permission>
</allow>
</access>
<dataset>
<alternateIdentifier system="Santa Cruz Island Reserve">AppNo_27840_ReserveID_16</alternateIdentifier>
<title>Landscape genetics of the western fence lizard (Sceloporus occidentalis becki) on Santa Cruz Island: the role of habitat complexity and climate on genetic connectivity of populations across the island.</title>
<creator>
<organizationName>Santa Cruz Island Reserve</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<organizationName>University of California Natural Reserve System</organizationName>
</creator>
<creator>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jeanne</givenName>
<surName>Robertson</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>California State University, Northridge</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>17950 Lassen St. Apt E4 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Northridge</city>
<administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>91325</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone>818-677-4408</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>jeanne.robertson@csun.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</creator>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Lynn</givenName>
<surName>McLaren</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Gregory</givenName>
<surName>Pauly</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>W. Chris</givenName>
<surName>Funk</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Jason</givenName>
<surName>Warner</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Michael</givenName>
<surName>Mousselli</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<metadataProvider><individualName>
<givenName>Eva</givenName>
<surName>Fischer</surName>
</individualName>
</metadataProvider>
<associatedParty><individualName>
<givenName>Jeanne</givenName>
<surName>Robertson</surName>
</individualName>
<role>associatedParty</role>
</associatedParty>
<associatedParty><individualName>
<givenName>Jeanne</givenName>
<surName>Robertson</surName>
</individualName>
<role>Co-owner</role>
</associatedParty>
<pubDate>2014-01-17</pubDate>
<abstract>
<para>The California Channel Islands is home to several endemic species and sub-species of amphibians and reptiles, yet comprehensive studies of the genetic relationships of Channel Island reptile species has yet to be done. We propose to examine the landscape genetic structure of Sceloporus occidental becki on Santa Cruz Island (California Channel Islands National Park). Landscape genetics seeks to understand the role of environmental variables (habitat and climate) on the genetic connectivity of populations. Santa Cruz Island is the ideal setting for a landscape study, due to the rich biome diversity and dramatic topographic relief.  In addition to the biome diversity on the island, there are substantial climatic differences across the island, resulting in hot and dry habitats on the western part of the island, and cool and wet habitat on the eastern side of the mountain. These differences in habitat and climate could influence the fine-scale connectivity of populations.  This research will examine the role of habitat and climate as important mediating factors that limit gene flow across the island. We predict that both habitat and climate variation are important features that structure populations, but our landscape models are required to identify the specific variables that play the most significant role. Current genetic analyses might reveal that the western fence lizard is an island endemic. If so, then our landscape genetics study, which seeks to understand the factors most important for the maintaining the evolutionary relationships among populations on the island, becomes a conservation imperative.</para>
</abstract>
<keywordSet>
<keyword >endemic</keyword>
<keyword >amphibians</keyword>
<keyword >reptiles</keyword>
<keyword >genetic relationships</keyword>
<keyword >Sceloporus occidental becki </keyword>
<keyword >habitat</keyword>
<keyword >climate</keyword>
<keyword >gene flow</keyword>
<keyword >western fence lizard </keyword>
<keyword >island endemic</keyword>
<keyword >Western</keyword>
<keyword >fence</keyword>
<keyword >lizard</keyword>
<keyword >Sceloporus</keyword>
<keyword >landscape</keyword>
<keyword >genetics</keyword>
<keyword >gene</keyword>
<keywordThesaurus>None</keywordThesaurus>
</keywordSet>
<additionalInfo>
<para>Application Number 27840 Santa Cruz Island Reserve</para>
</additionalInfo>
<intellectualRights>
<para>other</para>
<para>-</para>
</intellectualRights>
<distribution>
<online>
<url>http://santacruz.nrs.ucsb.edu/</url>
</online>
</distribution>
<distribution>
<offline>
<mediumName>other -</mediumName>
</offline>
</distribution>
<coverage>
<temporalCoverage>
<rangeOfDates>
<beginDate>
<calendarDate>2013-08-09</calendarDate>
</beginDate>
<endDate>
<calendarDate>2014-08-01</calendarDate>
</endDate>
</rangeOfDates>
</temporalCoverage>
<geographicCoverage>
<geographicDescription>Santa Cruz Island Reserve Marine Science Institute, Natural Reserve System, University of California Santa Barbara CA 93106-6150 USA</geographicDescription>
<boundingCoordinates>
<westBoundingCoordinate>-119.7333</westBoundingCoordinate>
<eastBoundingCoordinate>-119.7333</eastBoundingCoordinate>
<northBoundingCoordinate>34.0000</northBoundingCoordinate>
<southBoundingCoordinate>34.0000</southBoundingCoordinate>
</boundingCoordinates>
</geographicCoverage>
<taxonomicCoverage>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>species</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>Sceloporus</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>genus</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>occidentalis</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
<taxonomicClassification>
  <taxonRankName>genus</taxonRankName>
  <taxonRankValue>becki</taxonRankValue>
</taxonomicClassification>
</taxonomicCoverage>
</coverage>
<contact>
<individualName>
<givenName>Jeanne</givenName>
<surName>Robertson</surName>
</individualName>
<organizationName>California State University, Northridge</organizationName>
<address>
<deliveryPoint>17950 Lassen St. Apt E4 </deliveryPoint>
<city>Northridge</city>
<administrativeArea>California</administrativeArea>
<postalCode>91325</postalCode>
<country>United States</country>
</address>
<phone>818-677-4408</phone>
<electronicMailAddress>jeanne.robertson@csun.edu</electronicMailAddress>
</contact>
<methods><methodStep><description><section>
<title>Landscape genetics of the western fence lizard (Sceloporus occidentalis becki) on Santa Cruz Island: the role of habitat complexity and climate on genetic connectivity of populations across the island.</title>
<para>We will sample western fence lizards from 30 sites, distributed across Santa Cruz Island and targeting sites that represent the biome diversity of the island, as well as climatic variation. We will sample lizards from both the National Park Service and The Nature Conservancy properties. 

We will capture lizards using a fishing-line noose that is dangled from the end of a long fishing pole, standard methodology for capture reptiles (Savage 2002). This technique minimizes stress and reduces injury to the lizard. Lizard necks do not collapse, eliminating concern of strangulation using this technique. We will collect non-lethal DNA samples (tail tips) from 20 individuals from each of 30 sites distributed across Santa Cruz Island for a total of 600 samples. The number of individuals included in the study is standard and consistent with the number of individuals and populations required to answer questions regarding the genetic relationships among populations. We will also photograph (for coloration), weigh and measure all individuals. Each individual can be processed in 5 minutes. All animals will be returned to their exact point of capture. No animals will be euthanized for this study. We have obtained all the necessary permits and approval to conduct this study on TNC property (including California Fish and Game Scientific Collection Permit SCP-12495, approval from CSUN Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee Protocol # 1314-005a).</para>
<para></para>
<para>Permit Information: Project involves vertebrate animals.   Project involves reptiles.   Project involves capturing vertebrate animals.   Vertebrate animal's skin will be broken (needles, tags, surgery, etc.).   There is potential for any vertebrate animal's behavior to be altered.   Project involves taking, collecting, capturing, marking, or salvaging, mammals (except marine mammals), birds and their nests and eggs, reptiles, amphibians, fishes, invertebrates and/or marine algae.   
				</para>
</section></description></methodStep>
<sampling><studyExtent><description>
<para>2013-08-09 to  2014-08-01  We propose to study the entire island, including property of the National Park Service and The Nature Conservancy. We will collect non-lethal samples of the western fence lizard from sites that represent the biome diversity of the island, as well as climatic variation. The exact sample locations will be determined by the relative abundance of the western fence lizard. </para>
</description></studyExtent>
<samplingDescription>
<para>-</para>
</samplingDescription>
</sampling>
</methods>
</dataset>
</eml:eml>
