<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Kellner, Katrin</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Fernández-Marín, Hermogenes</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Ishak, Heather D.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Sen, Ruchira</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Linksvayer, Timothy A.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Mueller, Ulrich G.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-02-06T19:45:14Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2013-02-06T19:45:14Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Coevolutionary patterns and diversification of ant-fungus associations in the asexual fungus-farming ant Mycocepurus smithii in Panama</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cb850</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Partner fidelity through vertical symbiont transmission is thought to be the primary mechanism stabilizing cooperation in the mutualism between fungus-farming (attine) ants and their cultivated fungal symbionts. An alternate or additional mechanism could be adaptive partner or symbiont choice mediating horizontal cultivar transmission or de novo domestication of free-living fungi. Using microsatellite-genotyping for the attine ant Mycocepurus smithii and ITS rDNA-sequencing for fungal cultivars, we provide the first detailed population-genetic analysis of local ant-fungus associations to test for the relative importance of vertical versus horizontal transmission in a single attine species. M. smithii is the only known asexual attine ant, and it is furthermore exceptional because it cultivates a far greater cultivar diversity than any other attine ant. Cultivar switching could permit the ants to re-acquire cultivars after garden loss, to purge inferior cultivars that are locally mal-adapted or that accumulated deleterious mutations under long-term asexuality. Compared to other attine ants, symbiont choice and local adaptation of ant-fungus combinations may play a more important role than partner fidelity feedback in the co-evolutionary process of M. smithii and its fungal symbionts.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Coevolution</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>host specificity</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>host switching</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>thelytoky</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>mutualism</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>symbiosis</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Mycocepurus smithii</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Panama</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:spatial>Panama Canal Zone</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1111/jeb.12140</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.cb850/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>