<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Fay, Rémi</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Barbraud, Christophe</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Delord, Karine</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Weimerskirch, Henri</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-03-10T18:28:00Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2016-03-10T18:28:00Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Paternal but not maternal age influences early-life performance of offspring in a long-lived seabird</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8g531</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Variability in demographic traits between individuals within populations has profound implications for both evolutionary processes and population dynamics. Parental effects as a source of non-genetic inheritance are important processes to consider to understand the causes of individual variation. In iteroparous species, parental age is known to influence strongly reproductive success and offspring quality, but consequences on offspring fitness component after independence are much less studied. Based on a 37 years longitudinal monitoring of a long-lived seabird, the wandering albatross, we investigate delayed effects of parental age on offspring fitness components. We provide evidence that parental age influences offspring performance beyond the age of independence. By distinguishing maternal and paternal age effects, we demonstrate that paternal age, but not maternal age, impacts negatively post-fledging offspring performance.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Population ecology</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Agging</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Demography</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Wandering albatross</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2015.2318</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.8g531/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>