<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Zahawi, Rakan A.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Oviedo-Brenes, Federico</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Peterson, Chris J.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-08-24T13:14:37Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2017-08-24T13:14:37Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: A degradation debt? large-scale shifts in community composition and loss of biomass in a tropical forest fragment after 40 years of isolation</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.s5r8q</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Habitat loss and fragmentation are among the biggest threats to tropical biodiversity and associated ecosystem services. We examined forest dynamics in a mid-elevation 365-ha fragment in southern Costa Rica. The fragment was isolated in the mid-1970s and belongs to the Las Cruces Biological Station. A 2.25-ha permanent plot was established in the center of the old-growth forest (&gt;400 m to nearest edge boundary) and all plants &gt;5 cm DBH were censused, mapped, and identified to species in two surveys taken ~5–6 years apart (&gt;3,000 stems/survey). Although the reserve maintains high species richness (&gt;200 spp.), with many rare species represented by only one individual, we document a strong shift in composition with a two-fold increase in the number of soft-wooded pioneer individuals. The dominant late-successional understory tree species, Chrysochlamys glauca (Clusiaceae), and most species in the Lauraceae, declined dramatically. Turnover was high: 22.9% of stems in the first survey were lost, and 27.8% of stems in the second survey represented new recruits. Mean tree diameter decreased significantly and there was a 10% decrease in overall biomass. Such alteration has been documented previously but only in smaller fragments or within ~100 m of an edge boundary. Further penetration into this fragment was perhaps driven by a progressive invasion of disturbance-adapted species into the fragment’s core over time; the loss of once-dominant late successional species could be a contributing factor. The pattern found is of particular concern given that such fragments represent a substantial portion of today’s remaining tropical habitat; further studies in similar-sized fragments that have been isolated for similar prolonged periods are called for.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Fragmentation</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Tropical</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Degradation</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Forest</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>biomass</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Chrysochlamys glauca</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Hampea appendiculata</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Trophis mexicana</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Conostegia icosandra</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Lacistema aggregata</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Costa Rica</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:temporal>Holocene</dcterms:temporal>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0183133</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.s5r8q/1</dcterms:hasPart>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.s5r8q/2</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>