<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="urn:uuid:7a2cf7e8-6a84-404c-a791-d102109c5c66" system="https://arcticdata.io" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 eml.xsd">
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>NCEI Accession 0161176</alternateIdentifier>
    <alternateIdentifier>NODC Accession 0063065</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Arctic Ocean net primary productivity and water quality - Arctic System Science Primary Production observational synthesis project, 1954 - 2006</title>
    <creator id="5441386306233850">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Patricia</givenName>
        <surName>Matrai</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences, Maine, USA</organizationName>
      <positionName>Senior Research Scientist</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>60 Bigelow Drive</deliveryPoint>
        <city>East Boothbay</city>
        <administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>04544</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">2073152567</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pmatrai@bigelow.org</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://www.bigelow.org/about/people/pmatrai.html</onlineUrl>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1656-5519</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2019</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Arctic Ocean net primary productivity (NPP) was assembled for 1959-2011 from existing databases and recent polar research cruises. At each NPP station, if available, other data such as Chl-a, nitrate, and nitrite concentrations, mixed layer depth (MLD), SST, and euphotic layer depth were included. The data were obtained between 65 and 89°N mainly from late spring to early fall. At each station, NPP was measured at various depths using 13C- or 14C-labeled compounds. Surface fluorometric Chl-a concentration and SST were estimated from measurements between 0 and 5 m depth. MLD was estimated from CTD profiles using 0a threshold criterion. Nitrate and nitrite concentrations were measured only in the upper 100 m. Sponsored originally by NSF OPP ARCSS (1) and next by NASA through the Primary Productivity Algorithm Round Robin activity (PPARR) program. Data were provided in xlsx format and converted by NCEI to csv format. </para>
      <para>(1) Productivity, chlorophyll a, Photosynthetically Active Radiation (PAR) and other phytoplankton data from the Arctic Ocean, Bering Sea, Chukchi Sea, Beaufort Sea, East Siberian Sea, Kara Sea, Barents Sea, and Arctic Archipelago measured between 17 April, 1954 and 30 May, 2006 compiled as part of the Arctic System Science Primary Production (ARCSS-PP) observational synthesis project (NODC Accession 0063065)</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword>
      <keyword>Primary production</keyword>
      <keyword>biogeochemical cycles</keyword>
      <keyword>organic carbon</keyword>
      <keyword>chlorophyll</keyword>
      <keyword>Photosynthetically Active Radiation</keyword>
      <keyword>phytoplankton</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>GCMD</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This work is dedicated to the public domain under the Creative Commons Universal 1.0 Public Domain Dedication. To view a copy of this dedication, visit https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/.</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Arctic Ocean, Bering Sea, Chukchi Sea, Beaufort Sea, East Siberian Sea, Kara Sea, Barents Sea, and Arctic Archipelago</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-180</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>180</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>90</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>66</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1959</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2011</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact id="3809040500108810">
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Patricia</givenName>
        <surName>Matrai</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences, Maine, USA</organizationName>
      <positionName>Senior Research Scientist</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>60 Bigelow Drive</deliveryPoint>
        <city>East Boothbay</city>
        <administrativeArea>ME</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>04544</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">2073152567</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>pmatrai@bigelow.org</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://www.bigelow.org/about/people/pmatrai.html</onlineUrl>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1656-5519</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Arctic Ocean net primary productivity (NPP) was assembled for 1959-2011 from existing databases and polar research cruises. At each NPP station, if available, other data such as Chlorophyll-a (Chl-a), nitrate, and nitrite concentrations, mixed layer depth (MLD), sea surface temperature (SST), and euphotic layer depth were included. The data were obtained between 65 and 89°N mainly from late spring to early fall. At each station, NPP was measured at various depths using 13C- or 14C-labeled compounds. Surface fluorometric Chl-a concentration and SST were estimated from measurements between 0 and 5 m depth. MLD was estimated from CTD profiles using 0a threshold criterion. Nitrate and nitrite concentrations were measured only in the upper 100 m.</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>PRIMARY PRODUCTION (Measured)</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: Scintillation Counter; 13C- or 14C-based only</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>CHLOROPHYLL A CONCENTRATION (Measured)</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: fluorometer</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>TEMPERATURE WATER [WATER TEMPERATURE] (Measured)</para>
          <para>Unit: degrees Celsius</para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: CTD</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>NITRATE (Measured)</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: spectrophotometer</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>NITRITE (Measured)</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: spectrophotometer</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>NITRATE + NITRITE CONTENT (CONCENTRATION) (Measured)</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: spectrophotometer</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>LIGHT PENETRATION, ONE PERCENT LIGHT DEPTH (Measured)</para>
          <para>Unit: m</para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: PAR Sensor</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>MIXED LAYER DEPTH (Calculated)</para>
          <para>Unit: m</para>
          <para>Observation Category: in situ</para>
          <para>Sampling Instrument: CTD</para>
          <para>
            <superscript>-3</superscript>
            <superscript>-3</superscript>
          </para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>Suggested Author List:</para>
          <para>Lee, Younjoo J.; Matrai, Patricia A.; Friedrichs, Marjorie A. M.; Saba, Vincent S.; Ardyna, Mathieu; Babin, Marcel; Gosselin, Michel; Hirawake, Toru; Kang, SungHo; Lee, Sang H.;</para>
          <para>.</para>
          <para>References:</para>
          <para>Lee, Y. J., et al. (2015), An assessment of phytoplankton primary productivity in the Arctic Ocean from satellite ocean color/in situ chlorophyll a based models, J. Geophys. Res. Oceans, 120, 6508–6541, doi:10.1002/2015JC011018.</para>
          <para>Lee, Y. J., et al. (2016), Net primary productivity estimates and environmental variables in the</para>
          <para>Arctic Ocean: An assessment of coupled physical biogeochemical models, J. Geophys. Res. Oceans, 121, doi:10.1002/2016JC011993.</para>
          <para>Matrai, P.A. (2013), Synthesis of primary production in the Arctic Ocean: I. Surface waters, 1954-2007, Progr. Oceanogr., 110: 93–106, doi:10.1016/j.pocean.2012.11.004.</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <sampling>
        <studyExtent>
          <description>
            <para>Historical data were collected by many investigators and expeditions across the entire Arctic Ocean, preferentially in summer and scarcest in winter. Spatially, most stations were in ice-free, open waters and marginal ice zones;  with less in ice-covered waters. Please see Lee et al. 2015 and 2016 for station maps.</para>
          </description>
        </studyExtent>
        <samplingDescription>
          <para>No sampling description provided.</para>
        </samplingDescription>
      </sampling>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Collaborative Research: Understanding Arctic Marine Biogeochemical Response to Climate Change for Seasonal to Decadal Prediction Using Regional and Global Climate System Models</title>
      <personnel id="3842339346757808">
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Patricia</givenName>
          <surName>Matrai</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences, Maine, USA</organizationName>
        <positionName>Senior Research Scientist</positionName>
        <role>principalInvestigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The Arctic Ocean is experiencing rapid and dramatic environmental changes related to global warming. These changes affect the arctic marine carbon cycle as part of complex and coupled system interactions between the ocean, atmosphere, cryosphere and land surfaces, with important feedbacks to the global Earth System, including altering the concentration of atmospheric greenhouse gases. Previous and ongoing studies have laid the foundations for improving the understanding of arctic carbon sinks and sources using observational studies, regional ice-ocean modeling, and recent global carbon cycle simulations. However, there remain large uncertainties in the understanding of variability and change in the arctic marine carbon budget that are difficult to reconcile with existing tools.</para>
        <para>
This project will use the Regional Arctic System Model, comprised of marine biogeochemistry components in the eddy-resolving ocean and sea ice models to advance understanding and prediction of the arctic biogeochemical system, including shelf-basin and vertical nutrient exchange, the subsurface chlorophyll maximum, ice edge and under ice blooms and their role in ecosystem response to climate change. It builds on the recent and ongoing research by the team of investigators, including the development and evaluation of the marine biogeochemistry components for global sea ice/ocean models and the high resolution Regional Arctic System Model. The model simulates mass and energy exchange between sea ice, ocean, atmosphere and land on decadal timescales, with regionally constrained variability using observationally based atmospheric and oceanic datasets at lateral boundaries. The research will: (i) evaluate and refine the established ocean marine biogeochemistry model, and (ii) add a newly developed sea ice algal biogeochemistry component within the existing model infrastructure. These model enhancements will help better quantify variability, complexity, and change in arctic marine primary production. The overarching goal of this study is to achieve a comprehensive understanding of interactions between physical system components and the arctic marine carbon cycle, and to advance arctic system prediction at seasonal to centennial time scales with quantified uncertainty. </para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>1417517</para>
      </funding>
    </project>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
