<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Bruns, Emily L.</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Antonovics, Janis</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Carasso, Valentina</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Hood, Michael</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-02-13T17:08:24Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2017-02-13T17:08:24Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Transmission and temporal dynamics of anther-smut disease (Microbotryum) on alpine carnation (Dianthus pavonius)</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.vn707</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>1. Theory has shown that sterilizing diseases with frequency-dependent transmission (characteristics shared by many sexually transmitted diseases) can drive host populations to extinction. 2. Anther-smut disease (caused by Microbotryum sp.) has become a model plant pathogen system for studying the dynamics of vector and sexually transmitted diseases: infected individuals are sterilized, producing spores instead of pollen, and the disease is spread between reproductive individuals by insect pollinators. We investigated anther-smut disease in a heavily infected population of Dianthus pavonius (alpine carnation) over an eight-year period to determine disease impacts on host population dynamics. 3. Over the eight years, disease prevalence remained consistently high (&gt;40%) while the host population numbers declined by over 50%. 4. The observed rate of vector transmission to reproductive, adult hosts was inadequate to explain the high disease prevalence. Additional density-dependent aerial transmission to highly susceptible juveniles, indicated from experimental field and greenhouse studies, is likely to play a key role in maintaining the high disease prevalence. 5. Epidemiological models that accounted for the mixed transmission mode predicted an eventual decline in disease. 6. Synthesis: Our results demonstrate that high prevalence of a sterilizing disease does not necessarily drive host populations towards extinction and also highlights the importance of demographic studies for establishing the presence of alternative transmission modes.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>Epidemiology</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>age-specific resistance</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Demography</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>frequency-dependent transmission</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>mixed transmission</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>plant pathogen</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>sterilizing disease</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>vector transmission</dcterms:subject>
  <dwc:scientificName>Dianthus pavonius</dwc:scientificName>
  <dwc:scientificName>Microbotryum</dwc:scientificName>
  <dcterms:spatial>Italy</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12751</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.vn707/2</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>