<DryadDataPackage xmlns="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1" xmlns:dwc="http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/terms/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:bibo="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/dryad-bibo/v3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://purl.org/dryad/schema/terms/v3.1 http://datadryad.org/profile/v3.1/dryad.xsd">
  <dcterms:type>package</dcterms:type>
  <dcterms:creator>Deiss, Leonardo</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>de Moraes, Anibal</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:creator>Maire, Vincent</dcterms:creator>
  <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-08-07T11:31:19Z</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
  <dcterms:available>2018-08-07T11:31:19Z</dcterms:available>
  <dcterms:title>Data from: Environmental drivers of soil phosphorus composition in natural ecosystems</dcterms:title>
  <dcterms:identifier>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.f45f410</dcterms:identifier>
  <dcterms:description>Abstract. Soil organic and inorganic phosphorus (P) compounds can be influenced by distinctive environmental properties. This study aims to analyze soil P composition in natural ecosystems, relating organic (inositol hexakisphosphate, DNA and phosphonates) and inorganic (orthophosphate, polyphosphate and pyrophosphate) compounds with major temporal (weathering), edaphic and climatic characteristics. A dataset including 88 sites was assembled from published papers that determined soil P composition using one-dimensional liquid state 31P nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy of NaOH-EDTA extracts of soils. Bivariate and multivariate regression models were used to better understand the environmental properties influencing soil P. In bivariate relationships, trends for soil P compounds were similar for mineral and organic layers but with different slopes. Independent and combined effects of weathering, edaphic and climatic properties of ecosystems explained up to 78% (inositol hexakisphosphates) and 89% (orthophosphate) of variations in organic and inorganic P compounds across the ecosystems, likely deriving from parent material differences. Soil properties, particularly pH, total carbon, and carbon-to-phosphorus ratios, over climate and weathering mainly explained the P variation. We conclude that edaphic and climatic drivers regulate key ecological processes that determine the soil P composition in natural ecosystems. These processes are related to the source of P inputs, primarily determined by the parent material and soil forming factors, plant and microbe P cycling, the bio-physico-chemical properties governing soil phosphatase activity, soil solid surface specific reactivity, and P losses through leaching, and finally the P persistence induced by the increasing complexity of organic and inorganic P compounds as the pedogenesis evolves. Soil organic and inorganic P compounds respond differently to combinations of environmental drivers, which likely indicates that each P compound has specific factors governing its presence in natural ecosystems.</dcterms:description>
  <dcterms:subject>phosphorus</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>ecosystem</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>soil</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>nuclear magnetic resonance</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>climate</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>Structural equation modeling</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>boreal</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>temperate</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>tropical</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:subject>desert</dcterms:subject>
  <dcterms:spatial>Global</dcterms:spatial>
  <dcterms:temporal>Holocene</dcterms:temporal>
  <dcterms:references>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-15-4575-2018</dcterms:references>
  <dcterms:hasPart>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.f45f410/1</dcterms:hasPart>
</DryadDataPackage>